<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Francisco Lobos</title><link href="http://franciscolobos.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://franciscolobos.com/feeds/all-en.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://franciscolobos.com/</id><updated>2014-08-16T03:55:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Two Instapaper bookmarklets</title><link href="http://franciscolobos.com//en/instapaper-bookmarklets" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-08-16T03:55:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Francisco Lobos</name></author><id>tag:franciscolobos.com,2014-08-16:en/instapaper-bookmarklets</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As a child, I read everything I could get my hands on: books, magazines, newspapers, etc. That hasn&amp;rsquo;t changed much, except that now I read mainly articles on the internet. This is where &lt;a href="https://www.instapaper.com/"&gt;Instapaper&lt;/a&gt; comes into play. It helps me to keep things I can&amp;rsquo;t read right away, and check them later when I have more time. However, I tend to accumulate more than what I can read in my free time. To tackle this problem, I made ​​a couple of bookmarklets that improve my experience with this tool.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Random article&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I don&amp;rsquo;t know which article should I read. In such cases I let the computer decide for me. Looking around I found &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/sillygwailo/8871248"&gt;this bookmarklet&lt;/a&gt;, which I modified a bit to suit my needs. Depending on where you are when you click on it, this bookmarklet can do two things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re not in Instapaper&amp;rsquo;s first page (&lt;code&gt;http://www.instapaper.com/u&lt;/code&gt;), it redirects you there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But, if you&amp;rsquo;re already there, it chooses an article at random from that page and clicks it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To install the bookmarklet, drag the following link to your bookmarks bar.
&lt;a href="javascript:$('.meta_read_time').each(function(){var e='limegreen',t=parseInt($(this).text().slice(2,5),10);if(t&amp;gt;=20){e='red'}else if(t&amp;gt;=10){e='orange'}$(this).css({'background-color':e,color:'white',border:'2px solid '+e})})"&gt;Instapaper: Random&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also check the code in &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/flobosg/a2276c80483a4aa01740"&gt;this Github Gist&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Highlight reading times&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike their mobile equivalents, the Instapaper web app has no option to filter o sort articles according to their duration. When I have little time to read something, there is no quick way to identify short articles. That&amp;rsquo;s why, according to each article&amp;rsquo;s duration, this bookmarklet colors reading times green (0-9 min), orange (10-19 min) or red (≥ 20 min).&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/media/img/instapaper.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the bookmarklet:
&lt;a href="javascript:$('.meta_read_time').each(function(){var color;var time = $(this).text();time = time[1] === '%C2%B7' ? parseInt(time.slice(2)) : parseInt(time);if (time &amp;gt;= 20){color = 'red';} else if (time &amp;gt;= 10){color = 'orange';} else {color = &amp;quot;limegreen&amp;quot;;} $(this).css({'background-color': color, 'color': 'white', 'border': '2px solid '+color});})"&gt;Instapaper: Highlight times&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the other bookmarklet, this one is stored as &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/flobosg/4cfabe3d0592f65ad908"&gt;a Github Gist&lt;/a&gt; if you want to check it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it. If you are Instapaper users, I hope these bookmarklets are as useful to some of you as they are to me. Modify them, share them, tell your friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I took the opportunity to remember some Javascript and jQuery.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This would probably look better as an user script that loads with the page, but I like having the option to activate it only when I need it.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>I took a MOOC</title><link href="http://franciscolobos.com//en/mooc" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-08-27T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Francisco Lobos</name></author><id>tag:franciscolobos.com,2013-08-27:en/mooc</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks ago I finished &lt;a href="http://www.coursera.org/course/molevol"&gt;Computational Molecular Evolution&lt;/a&gt;, a &lt;abbr title=""&gt;MOOC&lt;/abbr&gt; (massive open online course) in Coursera taught by Anders Gorm Pedersen from the Technical University of Denmark (&lt;abbr title=""&gt;DTU&lt;/abbr&gt;). I joined it because I wanted to review some concepts related to phyloinformatics learnt during my undergraduate years. This is the first course of this kind that I took and have been very satisfied with it, so I thought it would be nice to share my impressions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite being the first one, I consider this course an example of a well-executed &lt;abbr title=""&gt;MOOC&lt;/abbr&gt;. Professor Pedersen showed a good understanding of the subjects, which was reflected in the clarity of the explanations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of a virtual machine with Xubuntu was a great idea, allowing the standardization of the exercises and letting us work like the experts do in real life. Too bad that one of the programs used (&lt;a href="http://paup.csit.fsu.edu/"&gt;&lt;abbr title=""&gt;PAUP&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) is paid, although there are free alternatives, such as &lt;a href="http://www.megasoftware.net/"&gt;&lt;abbr title=""&gt;MEGA&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://evolution.genetics.washington.edu/phylip.html"&gt;&lt;abbr title=""&gt;PHYLIP&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each practical quiz was conceived as a step-by-step tutorial, explaining the meaning of each command and its theoretical background. It was noticeable the fact that these exercises were previously tested and polished, which I appreciate, since I had no difficulties to follow them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wish the course had covered more topics (bootstrapping, for example), although I think that the content selection was accurate and covers the topic of computational phylogenetics fairly well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The topics were covered with an adequate depth. However, I would like recommendations of scientific articles related to the theory or application of the subjects discussed in the lectures. Some of that was shown in the lecture about reconstruction of ancestral sequences.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I understand that maybe it wasn&amp;rsquo;t one of the main objectives of the course, but I was left wanting more. It would have been nice to know some real life examples. For instance, nothing was mentioned about computational phylogenetics in a clinical or epidemiological setting.&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It&amp;rsquo;s not a serious issue, but I would have liked to see it on the course. Call me picky if you want to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time I enrolled at the course I was afraid that the course would be difficult or it would require a lot of time, which would had forced me to abandon it. Fortunately, that idea never entered my head. Instead, each week I was glued to the monitor watching the lectures, while concepts that previously were hard to assimilate became familar to me. At the end of last quiz I found myself wanting more, something that few classroom courses managed to achieve! I can only thank Professor Pedersen and the staff from Coursera and &lt;abbr title=""&gt;DTU&lt;/abbr&gt; who made this course possible, for sharing their time and knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly this &lt;abbr title=""&gt;MOOC&lt;/abbr&gt; set the bar high for future courses of this type I intend to take. In fact, I already took two more, related to biostatistics: &lt;a href="http://www.coursera.org/course/casebasedbiostat"&gt;Case-Based Introduction to Biostatistics&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.coursera.org/course/biostats"&gt;Biostatistics Mathematical Boot Camp 1&lt;/a&gt;. They will probably be more difficult than Computational Molecular Evolution, but that&amp;rsquo;s a topic for another post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even giving examples outside the biological field, such as the inference of original manuscripts.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.wired.com/wiredscience/2013/01/ff-kpc-superbug-nih/all/"&gt;This article&lt;/a&gt; by Carl Zimmer in Wired last January comes to mind. It&amp;rsquo;s about a carbapenem-resistant &lt;em&gt;Klebsiella pneumoniae&lt;/em&gt; outbreak in a hospital.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>A presenter screen for Impressive</title><link href="http://franciscolobos.com//en/impressive-presenter" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-02-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Francisco Lobos</name></author><id>tag:franciscolobos.com,2013-02-18:en/impressive-presenter</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I ditched presentation software a while ago. Now I make my slides in &lt;abbr title=""&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt; and show them with a document reader.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Recently I&amp;rsquo;ve been checking out Impressive, a program written in Python that displays &lt;abbr title=""&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt; presentation slides using OpenGL. It contains some unique features, but sometimes a presenter screen comes in handy, and sadly, &lt;a href="http://impressive.sourceforge.net/faq.php"&gt;Impressive doesn&amp;rsquo;t come with one&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a corollary to PyGame&amp;rsquo;s inability to support multiple monitors or even multiple windows, it is also not possible to have a presenter screen like OpenOffice or Keynote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know there are alternatives, such as &lt;a href="http://westhoffswelt.de/projects/pdf_presenter_console.html"&gt;pdf-presenter-console&lt;/a&gt;, which is good, but rather basic and lacks some features I like from Impressive, such as transitions and the overview screen. Luckily, Seppe vanden Broucke came up with &lt;a href="http://blog.macuyiko.com/2009/12/buillding-presenter-view-for-linux.html"&gt;a great solution&lt;/a&gt;. He built a presenter screen in &lt;abbr title=""&gt;HTML&lt;/abbr&gt;. Every time a slide is shown, and taking advantage of its scripting capabilities, Impressive writes some information to a &lt;abbr title=""&gt;JSON&lt;/abbr&gt; object stored in a plain text file. Then this file is loaded in the presenter screen using jQuery. Pretty neat, in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I took his code, changed some stuff, and made &lt;a href="http://github.com/flobosg/impressive-presenter"&gt;impressive-presenter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="impressive-presenter" src="/media/img/impressive-presenter.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This workflow is recommended:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make your &lt;abbr title=""&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt; slides however you like.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run &lt;code&gt;impressive-presenter.sh&lt;/code&gt; with your presentation file as an argument. It will create some files in the presentation directory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://impressive.sourceforge.net/manual.php#scripts"&gt;Modify the &lt;code&gt;.info&lt;/code&gt; file&lt;/a&gt; if you need to (for transitions, for example). The &lt;code&gt;notes&lt;/code&gt; property will be shown on the presenter screen as speaker notes. &lt;abbr title=""&gt;HTML&lt;/abbr&gt; is allowed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At the time of your presentation, open &lt;code&gt;presenter.html&lt;/code&gt; in your laptop screen.&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the main screen, start your presentation with Impressive. If everything goes well, &lt;code&gt;presenter.html&lt;/code&gt; should update its info.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a quick and dirty solution, but one advantage of this approach is that if you know &lt;abbr title=""&gt;HTML&lt;/abbr&gt; and &lt;abbr title=""&gt;CSS&lt;/abbr&gt;, the presenter screen is fully customizable. Anyway, if you want to give it a shot, &lt;a href="http://github.com/flobosg/impressive-presenter"&gt;the code is available at GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use LibreOffice Impress to make the presentations and export them to &lt;abbr title=""&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;, but I&amp;rsquo;m considering the switch to desktop publishing software like InDesign or Scribus. Beamer bores the hell out of me.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Chrome, you&amp;rsquo;ll need to execute the browser with the &lt;code&gt;--allow-file-access-from-files&lt;/code&gt; flag, otherwise it won&amp;rsquo;t work. This flag could change without notice, so be careful and check the &lt;a href="http://peter.sh/experiments/chromium-command-line-switches/"&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt;. Or just use another browser.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Dvorak for Latin Americans</title><link href="http://franciscolobos.com//en/latam-dvorak" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-01-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Francisco Lobos</name></author><id>tag:franciscolobos.com,2013-01-13:en/latam-dvorak</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of my goals this year is to learn to type in Dvorak, to check if they are certain they have the wonders of that layout. Increased typing rate, better ergonomics, fewer errors? Count me in! &lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, I intend to use the Spanish variant, which is similar to the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dvorak_Simplified_Keyboard"&gt;English one&lt;/a&gt;, except that the R and H keys are swapped. However, there is a small detail regarding Spanish keyboard layouts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some strange reason, QWERTY layouts for Spanish are available in two variants: Spanish and Latin American Spanish.&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Their differences lie in the location of the symbols and the presence (or absence) of some of them. One of the simplest changes you may notice is the position of the at sign (@): in Spanish is is located on the key with the number 2, while the Latin American layout has it on the key for the letter Q.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To my surprise, Ubuntu (or rather, X.Org) only has a Dvorak layout for Spanish. As the keyboard of my notebook has a Latin American layout, and I don&amp;rsquo;t intend to memorize the position of each symbol, I decided to do some research and create (with &lt;a href="http://hektor.umcs.lublin.pl/~mikosmul/computing/articles/custom-keyboard-layouts-xkb.html"&gt;some&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.charvolant.org/~doug/xkb/"&gt;help&lt;/a&gt;) a Dvorak variant for Latin American Spanish, which I uploaded to &lt;a href="http://github.com/flobosg/latam-dvorak"&gt;this repository on Github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="latam-dvorak layout" src="/media/img/latam-dvorak.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if you use a Spanish keyboard, you&amp;rsquo;re a fan of Dvorak, but not of the cedilla (ç) or the euro symbol (€), and you hate to see a grave accent (`) when you want to type an acute one (´), check it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I recommend trying at a time when you&amp;rsquo;re not writing something important (like a thesis project).&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spanish is also known as Spanish (International Sort).&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary></entry></feed>